<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>D.E. defeated, or, A reply to a late scurrilous pamphlet vented against the Lord Bishop of Worcester's letter, whereby he vindicated himself from Mr. Baxter's misreports. / By S.H.</title>
            <author>Holden, Samuel, fl. 1662-1676.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1662</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 72 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 18 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A44125</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing H2381</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R19194</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12171879</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12171879</idno>
            <idno type="VID">55433</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A44125)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 55433)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English Books, 1641-1700 ; 603:12 or 2265:12)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>D.E. defeated, or, A reply to a late scurrilous pamphlet vented against the Lord Bishop of Worcester's letter, whereby he vindicated himself from Mr. Baxter's misreports. / By S.H.</title>
                  <author>Holden, Samuel, fl. 1662-1676.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 31 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for R. Royston, at the Angel in Ivy-Lane,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>M.DC.LXII. [1662]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Item at 603:12 is incorrectly identified as Wing H2381 in reel guide.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of originals in University of Illinois (Urbana-Champaign Campus). Library and Lambeth Palace Library, London, England.</note>
                  <note>An answer to Edward Bagshaw's Letter to a person of honour which is a reply to George Morley's Letter to a friend.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Morley, George, 1597-1684.</term>
               <term>Bagshaw, Edward, 1629-1671. --  Letter unto a person of honour.</term>
               <term>Baxter, Richard, 1615-1691.</term>
               <term>Bishops --  England --  Temporal power --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>Jayanthi Reddy</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>Jayanthi Reddy</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:55433:1"/>
            <p>
               <hi>D. E.</hi> DEFEATED: OR, A REPLY TO A Late Scurrilous Pamphlet Vented againſt the Lord Biſhop of <hi>Worceſter's</hi> Letter, Whereby he Vindicated himſelf from Mr. <hi>BAXTER'S</hi> Miſreports.</p>
            <p>By <hi>S. H.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <p>Qui benè audire velit, loquatur benè.</p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Sen.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed for <hi>R. Royſton,</hi> at the <hi>Angel</hi> in <hi>Ivy-lane.</hi> M.DC.LXII.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:55433:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:55433:2"/>
            <head>
               <hi>Preface to the</hi> READER.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Courteous Reader,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hink not that I have preſum'd to defend his Lordſhip's Letter, or arrogated to my ſelf the ſupport of his <hi>Epiſtolary</hi> treatiſe. No, I know his Merits to be out of the reach of Detraction, his Perſon beyond the venom of the moſt maligning Spleen; and his Letter to tranſcend all rati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onal Exception. My deſign therefore is, to ſtop the mouth of this unmanner'd <hi>Coridon;</hi> whoſe Drift is to build himſelf a Name in the Slander of Grandees, and to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come notorious by expoſing deſerts to the malice and miſprizion of diſaffected Perſons.</p>
            <p>There are, I know, many inconveniences that might have ſcar'd me from the enterprize. I am not unac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted with the Epidemical fate of thoſe who have ingag'd into Controverſies, in that they common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly encounter an unhappy Dilemma; for upon any (though never ſo inconſiderable an) Anſwer, they muſt either gratifie their Adverſary by a reſolved Silence, or elſe ſweat in the invincible Cacoethes of a frequent Reply. Beſides this; to affrighten me, there was a Bear in the way: for the Perſon (a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt whom I have rays'd the weapons) hath in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curr'd an honourable: Scandal in the mouths of ſome, who have reputed him a Make-bate Jeſuite; But this difficulty I vanquiſhed in a ſhort and eaſie meditation, for (although I knew he might eaſily be induc'd to make as virulent a Diſcovery of his Malice, yet) I could ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver be tempted to believe that a Jeſuite would ever have befriended us with ſuch an ample diſcloſure of
<pb facs="tcp:55433:3"/>his ignorance. And indeed this was the ground on which I overcame one of the forementioned Praemunire's of the Preſs, not dreading even the quotidian iteration of his Reply, whoſe indiſcretion ſufficiently ſatisfy'd me of my Security. So that the encouragement which animated me to the cloſure with <hi>D.E.</hi> (for that is all the ear-mark we have of him) lies obvious and viſible. But yet (Gentle Reader) the Suit that ſent me to thy Courteſie, remans ſtill undiſcovered.</p>
            <p>Deſiring thee therefore to know, that I have dealt more fairly with his, than he with his Lordſhips Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, (not ſnapping at a few glean'd Particulars; but re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plying to the moſt conſiderable part thereof) I muſt fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtall thy further view with a double Requeſt, <hi>(1)</hi> That I may be excuſed in that I have rebandied language of his own Complexion upon him; finding no unſutable<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs in that advice, viz. <hi>Anſwer a fool according to his folly,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>(2)</hi> That I may be diſpens'd with, in that I have not made it my buſineſs ſo much to entertain thee with demonſtrative Arguments, in behalf of thoſe things which <hi>D.E.</hi> ſcruples; as by ſatisfactory Anſwers to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form thee of the invalidity of his exceptions. Since I thought it the ſtrongeſt probation of thoſe aſſertions, at which he carps, to expoſe to thy view the vanity and emptineſs of his Allegations againſt them. Moreover, I ſhould probably have wrought him into ſome partial conceit of himſelf, had I anſwer'd his Pamphlet with a Volume. However, waive not the reading of theſe few leaves out of any deſpondency of ſatisfaction, till thy peruſing eye ſhall acquaint thee with the Contents.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Thine, &amp;c. <hi>S. H.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="pamphlet">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:55433:3"/>
            <head>
               <hi>D. E.</hi> DEFEATED: OR, A REPLY TO A Late Scurrilous Pamphlet Vented againſt the Lord Biſhop of <hi>WORCESTER,</hi> &amp;c.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> 
               <hi>Am</hi> (ſaith <hi>D. E.</hi>) <hi>to thank you for the laſt piece of Divertiſement you gave me in ſending the Biſhop of</hi> Worceſter<hi>'s Letter.</hi> The Spleen of <hi>Democri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus</hi> was nothing to the humour of this fellow. His life (to whom ſuch ſolid matters were but Divertiſements) was ſure very jocular; and the merry temper of other Naturals, falls much beneath it. But he proceeds: <hi>And I wiſh you would have let me enjoy'd the ſatisfaction I took in reading it without engaging me to give you my ſenſe upon it. Senſe</hi> did he call it? I ever thought Senſe to have been a little more of kin to Reaſon. But I am ready to gratifie him ſo far, as to father the miſtake on the Printer, and to ſuppoſe it ſhould have been <hi>Non-ſenſe.</hi> But
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:55433:4"/>ſenſe let it be; and let him give his Parron this his ſenſe; I think he was ſo generous in giving it, that he improvi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently reſerv'd none at all for himſelf. But he annexe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>h, <hi>For beſides my unwillingneſs to engage in a perſonal quarrel, I think it will not be very ſafe medling with ſo angry an ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſary.</hi> Never fear it Man! Never fear it! <hi>Scaraboeos contemnunt Aquilae.</hi> Think not that he will adopt to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf ſo much unquietneſs as to deam of you. What though he be a Man of worth and eminence? yet, his Gravity will not diſpenſe with his entertaining fools in his thoughts, or encouraging a red Cap with notice and ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation. Next, <hi>D. E. reſolves to ſpeak nothing but truth in the Character he intends to give him, and it is briefly this, That in fewer leaves he never read more paſſion. Spectatum admiſſi riſum teneatis?</hi> I thought his ſenſe would come to this anon. He pretends to give us a Character of the Biſhop, and he tells us the Contents of his Book. His preceding words promiſe an appoſite Deſcription of his Lordſhips perſon, and his next ſyllables acquaint us with nothing at all to the purpoſe, but only, <hi>that in fewer leaves</hi> D. E. <hi>never read more paſſion.</hi> Well, for once then let me preſent the Reader with a Character of the <hi>Biſhop;</hi> and 'tis briefly this, That <hi>D. E.</hi> is an arrant Aſſe. Both de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcriptions are alike to the purpoſe. But he tells us, <hi>that the Biſhops book is full of paſſion;</hi> And is there not in our Authors Reply, a thouſand times more of Malice and Rankour (I dare not ſay, <hi>Paſſion;</hi> for that's ſoly incident to rational creatures)? But, <hi>the Biſhops paſſion is ſo predomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, that his diſorderly and abrupt ſtile doth altogether par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take of it.</hi> He accuſes a ſtyle compos'd of Gravity, as blended with abruption and bitterneſs, whereas his par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takes of either (the laſt eſpecially) in a far more intenſe degree. 'Twas an Errata ſure in the Satyriſt, <hi>Dum vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant ſtulti vitia, in contraria currunt.</hi> For here's one or'e head and ears in Rayllery, whileſt he not only pretends to eſchew it, but hath the face even to declare againſt it. Next we are informed, that <hi>the Biſhops beſt way will be to get his heat miſtaken for zeal; for elſe it may juſtly be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:55433:4"/>ſomewhat of a worſe name, and which in the Dog-dayes will be very dangerous.</hi> Though <hi>D. E.</hi> belies the Lord Biſhop's Letter as ſavouring of heat; yet I'me ſure tis far from abuſe or ſcandal, to pronounce the quinteſſence of <hi>D. E.</hi> his Pamphlet, vapour and ſmoak. But may we not juſtly admire how our Pamphleter came acquainted with the danger of the Dog-dayes, or the influence of a Star? unleſs perhaps by barking againſt the Moon, to which cuſtom he hath not yet bid adieu. If I might be of his Counſel, I ſhould adviſe him, as his beſt courſe, not to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to Aſtronomy, whom a <hi>Cudgel</hi> doth better become than a <hi>Jacob</hi>'s <hi>ſtaff.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Our Replicant makes no long abode on the contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted Queſtion, either becauſe he did not well under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand the State, and was loath to diſplay his igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance: Or elſe, becauſe he could not find a plauſible occaſion to vent that Rancour, from the exuberant ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plies of which, he hath borrowed a Ninefold Excep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion againſt ſome particular occurrences in the Lord Biſhop's Letter, where he ſuppos'd himſelf capable of faſtening. Indeed he would perſwade us, that 'twas his inclination to <hi>Favour the Biſhop,</hi> made him waive the main Diſpute. But thanks be to his <hi>Ignorance,</hi> rather than his <hi>Clemency.</hi> However, though I cannot believe him, yet I will not ſtand to queſtion him, but wait upon him in his Exceptions.</p>
            <div n="1" type="exception">
               <head>I. EXCEPT.</head>
               <p>HE takes much in dudgeon that Aſſeveration of the reciprocal alliance between Kings and Biſhops, in the Proverb, <hi>No BISHOP, no KING.</hi> Neither doth <hi>D. E.</hi> ſee any Dependence they have each on other, thinking <hi>Epiſcopacy to contribute little or nothing to the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtence of the King's Authority.</hi> But we muſt deſire him
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:55433:5"/>to be informed, that this Cohaerence doth (although ſomething, yet) not ſo much reſult from any poſitive reſpect in themſelves; as from that inconſiſtency which is between any other Eccleſiaſtical Government, and <hi>Kingſhip.</hi> For either we muſt ſuppoſe an aequality of Degrees amongſt Eccleſiaſtical Perſons; or elſe the prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eminence and ſuperiority of <hi>Lay-Elders,</hi> (for I know no other Eccleſiaſtick ſtate whereunto any have inclined) now what a diametrical antipathy and oppoſition either of theſe two Conditions bear to a <hi>Regall Supremacy,</hi> is eaſily demonſtrated. For, as to the firſt, ſhould we ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe all Church-perſons, or Miniſters, empowr'd with equal authority, that indiſtinction would redound no leſſe to his Majeſty's diſadvantage in Spirituals, (every man being in a poſture to broach his own opinion, or promote another's faction) than the Confuſion of a ſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar power in Leveldom, would endammage the Kings Temporal Domination. Or, ſecondly, Were we under the py-ball'd diſpoſing of Laicks; how could they (according to the exaction of their duty) devote themſelves to the Churches benefit? Since their double Intereſts would oblige them to diſtraction, and a damnable Neutrality that would juſtifie <hi>Eraſmus</hi> his Anomalous ſtate of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. Which, how far it would impair the Churches hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs, and conſequently plunder one ballance of the Kings Soveraignty (whoſe Eccleſiaſtical and Temporal State muſt counterpoiſe each other, that the Crown ſtand even) I leave to the judgement of any rational man.</p>
               <p>But to inquire into our Animadverter's Reaſons that prompted him to the diſavowing of any ſuch rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Saith he, <hi>Kings flowriſhed in all parts of the World, before Biſhops were ever heard of. And there can no reaſon be Given, why what hath once been, may not with the ſame terms of Covenience be again.</hi> As to the firſt aſſertion (<hi>viz.</hi> that the Antiquity of Kings doth far ſurpaſſe that of Biſhops) I muſt needs acknowledge it the trueſt propoſition in all
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:55433:5"/>the Pamphlet. For none can be ignorant that <hi>Ninus</hi> the firſt <hi>Aſſyrian</hi> Monarch flouriſh't without the leaſt ſupport of a Biſhop. We know that <hi>Zoroaſtres Magus,</hi> firſt King of the <hi>Bactrians,</hi> and the firſt writer that Hiſtory preſents unto us, neither had Biſhops in his Kingdom, nor yet ever men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned ſuch a Name in thoſe books he legacy'd to poſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity. Neither do we read that <hi>Croeſus, Cyrus, Darius, Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lip</hi> of <hi>Macedon,</hi> or his Son <hi>Alexander,</hi> made uſe of Biſhops. So that had <hi>D. E.</hi> left us nothing partaking more of falſity than this Poſition, I ſhould never have queſtioned him. But yet when all this is <hi>pro confeſſo,</hi> I wonder by what Infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence and deduction, he could tell us that we may with the <hi>ſame terms of convenience</hi> admit the <hi>ſame poſture of Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment again?</hi> For (1) What though he ſhould tell us, that the <hi>Mogul, Preſter John,</hi> or the Great <hi>Cham</hi> of <hi>Tartary,</hi> do to this day preſerve their Magnificence, without the leaſt concurrence of an Epiſcopal Juriſdiction? Doth it there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore follow, that a Chriſtian King may? They may alſo ſubſiſt without a Church, yea and do; but, is there the ſame <hi>Convenience</hi> for a King in <hi>Chriſtendom,</hi> ſo to do? Where there is no <hi>Eccleſiaſtick</hi> State, cannot be expected <hi>Eccleſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſtick</hi> Government. But where a Kings Prerogative hath a double aſpect (towards Spirituals, and towards Tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rals) there is required ſome juriſdiction in either; to which, States of a contrary conſtitution can neither preſcribe <hi>Names</hi> nor <hi>Method.</hi> Their Regimen without Biſhops, doth not at all involve any poſſibility of the ſame among us. (2) What though <hi>D. E.</hi> could (although he never can) prove, that even <hi>Chriſtian Kings</hi> have flouriſhed without Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops? Yet, doth it follow that <hi>England</hi> (for the Proverb was neither derived from nor is extended to, exotick Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions) may with the ſame facility diſpence with the pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation of them? Why ſhould the Sequel be good? Why ſhould other people become a neceſſary preſident to us? Or, why ſhould our Capacities be meaſured by their Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline? Since our humours are of another countenance, and (for the ſecurity of his Majeſty) may require a Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment partaking ſomewhat of ſingularity in Church;
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:55433:6"/>as well as diſtinct from others in State. Or (3), Should we ſuppoſe (for, <hi>demonſtrationis gratiâ,</hi> we may ſuppoſe <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> and impoſſibles) even in <hi>England,</hi> a Power called <hi>King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip</hi> without Biſhops; yet the veracity of the Maxim (<hi>No Biſhop, no King</hi>) would ſtand firm and unſhaken. For the Authority of a <hi>King,</hi> (as a <hi>King</hi>) is unconfin'd and abſolute, without the leaſt <hi>Apocope,</hi> mutilation, or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtriction of Command. And a King is not <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, or natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally call'd a King, when his luſtre is eclips'd in the derogating from his Soveraignty. So that, I ſay, although we ſhould ſuppoſe a Monarchical Government, preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the name of Kingſhip, to be deſtitute of Biſhops; yet it would not follow, that it would ſhine in its due ſplendour (and conſequently be <hi>Kingſhip</hi> properly ſo termed) without them. For the other two Eccleſiaſtick States (which ſome have dream'd of) would (as I ſaid be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore) if not ruine, yet, diminiſh his Majeſties Authority, and make his <hi>Kingſhip</hi> and <hi>Regal Power</hi> dwindle into ſomething of a more inconſiderable name. So that, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out his Biſhops, he would not be a King properly ſo cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led. We have ſeen that groſſe <hi>Non-ſequitur</hi> of <hi>D. E.</hi> viz. <hi>Kings have flouriſhed without Biſhops;</hi> ergo, <hi>they may ſtill.</hi> But this is only the firſt of his Reaſons which made him Scruple the mutual Relation of Kings and Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Saith <hi>D. E. Biſhops, as they are by law Eſtabliſhed in England, are purely the Kings ſubordinate Miniſters, in the Management of Eccleſiaſtical affairs, which his Majeſty may confer upon what order of men he pleaſeth, though as much lay-perſons us you and I.</hi> Hence, he concludes that there is no neceſſity of ſuch a mutual reſpect between Kings and Biſhops. Whether our Pamphleter be a Laick or no? I liſt not here to enquire, although his Ignorance beſpeaks him to be ſomewhat worſe. When he wrote this, he did it in ſo great ſimplicity, that his left hand knew not what his right hand did. For the queſtion is not, Whether his Majeſty may inveſt a Laick with Eccleſiaſtick dignities and promotions? but, Whether he may do it without detri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:55433:6"/>
                  <hi>to his Kingdom,</hi> and the unavoydable ruines of a Glorious Church, without which his Kingſhip would be at an ebb? We do not ſo farr detract from his Majeſty's Power, as to avow that he cannot ſubſtitute <hi>Mechanicks'</hi> in Church-diſcipline; But we ſay, that if He ſhould do it, it would not a little tend to the diſadvantage, prejudice, yea, ſubverſion of his Kingly Power. And whence then doth <hi>D. E.</hi> conclude the nullity of that coherence be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween <hi>Kings and Biſhops?</hi> There is a difference between the Kings doing a thing, and his doing it with ſafety. The King may infringe the connexion betwixt him and Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops, by his diſcarding them; But he cannot maintain his Regal Authority in ſuch a diſ-union. Hence then, 'tis abſolutely falſe, and nothing deductive from his premiſſes, which <hi>D. E.</hi> infers, <hi>viz. That 'tis very injurious to the King's authority to averr, that he could not otherwiſe uphold himſelf, than by preſerving the undue, and (as ſome think) Antichriſtian praelation of his inferiour officers.</hi> Speak out man! Some think quoth a? The Man is loath to accuſe himſelf, but preſents it to us under the frantick conceit of his Brethren. <hi>Antichriſtian?</hi> Methinks, his own thoughts might have convinc'd him of the falſity of that paſſion; and he might have concluded a Biſhop to have been no kin to <hi>Antichriſt,</hi> ſince then, A Prelate and <hi>D. E.</hi> would have been better friends.</p>
               <p n="3">3. He will have us believe that <hi>Biſhops are ſo little uſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful to ſupport the Regal dignity, that none have been greater enemies to the Kings undoubted Soveraignty than ſome Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops.</hi> Where we may obſerve the weakneſs of his Reaſon. Some Biſhops have abuſed the Kings truſt; therefore there is no reaſon why <hi>Epiſcopacy</hi> ſhould be entail'd to <hi>King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip.</hi> The ſame reaſon may be alleadged againſt No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility, ſince ſome Nobles have employ'd their honours and capacities to the diſtraction of the Kingdom and the endammagement of his Majeſty; hence might we con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude (did the method of <hi>D. E.</hi> hold good), that the King may ſubſiſt without his Nobles. Or, what if we ſhould recriminate, on thoſe <hi>Presbyterians</hi> who have ſurmis'd
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:55433:7"/>a <hi>Parliament</hi> eſſential to the Kingly Government, and tell them that ſome of the Parliament have made Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon the deſign of many conſultations, therefore the King might and ought to ſubſiſt without any ſuch But<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſſes and Appendixes of Domination? Sure, they would much grumble at ſuch an Argument. And <hi>D. E.</hi> would think little reaſon in it. But let us ſee, what ground he had to blemiſh any of the Biſhops, with ſtyling them <hi>Enemies to the Kings undoubted Soveraignty.</hi> They are ſo, ſaith he, <hi>either by their ſcarce warrantable intermedling in Civill af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs.</hi> Had he but inſtanced in ſome of thoſe affairs (as his malice would eaſily have done, had not his ignorance countermanded it), I ſhould have known better how to Reply. For I know no Secular buſineſs wherein any of them have, or do Authoritatively concern themſelves, or wherewith they do intermingle; unleſs the things be ſuch, as, carrying a double nature, have a greater allyance with Eccleſiaſtical, than Temporal Conſiderations; their by as directing towards the Church-intereſt. And as for their medling with ſuch matters, I ſee not how <hi>D. E.</hi> could term them Unwarrantable, or Prejudicial to the Kings undoubted Soveraignty. But this is not all the reaſon of his abuſing Biſhops, but the ſecond way whereby he deems them the Kings Enemies, is, <hi>By their abſurd and inſignificant diſtinguiſhing between Civil and Eccleſiaſtical Cauſes, whereby they mangle the Kings Authority, leaving him no Supremacy, as to Church-matters, but the Name.</hi> Whether our Author be a fit diſcerner of inſignificant di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinctions, let any judge. Why ſhould the differencing and diſcriminating of Cauſes into <hi>Civil</hi> and <hi>Eccleſiaſtick,</hi> be more abſurd than the diſtinguiſhing of perſons into ſuch? Beſides, who ſees not what a Scandalous lie he hath here vented? Whith what face could he ſay that the King is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed no Soveraignty in Church-affairs, but only nomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal, when his Majeſty may and doth like, diſapprove, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gulate, determine, and diſpoſe of them, how and when he himſelf pleaſeth? So that (although <hi>D. E.</hi> would falſely perſwade us the contrary) the Popes pretenſions are of a
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:55433:7"/>nature contradiſtinct to thoſe of our Biſhops; ſince his Supremacy admits of no acknowledgment of ſubordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. So that, the Pope is no more of kin to our Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops, than <hi>D. E.</hi> to Truth and Honeſty. If our Pam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phleter be ſo good at lying. I ſhould ſcarce truſt him this dear year, leſt he ſhould exerciſe his skill in another fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culty. But he proceeds: <hi>If the Biſhop of</hi> Worceſter's <hi>Rule hold good,</hi> —Crimine ab uno, Diſce omnes, — i. e. <hi>that all men of a party may be judged by the miſcarriage of one, then you may judge by the Biſhop of</hi> Worceſter, <hi>what the reſt drive at.</hi> What pains doth <hi>D. E.</hi> take in an expo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition? He would fain perſwade us that he underſtands Latin; when, it may be, he was obliged to the Civility of a <hi>Rider</hi>'s Dictionary. As for his retorting that ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence — <hi>Crimine ab uno, Diſce omnes</hi> — (urg'd by my Lord of <hi>Worceſter</hi> upon <hi>The Presbyterians</hi>) let me tell him, 'twas done without the leaſt dram of underſtanding. For, although we ſhould grant to <hi>D. E.</hi> that this one Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop (though it can never be proved) is guilty of Uſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pation, yet the Phraſe cannot with the ſame reaſon be rebandied on Epiſcopacy through his default, who is farre from engroſſing the name of <hi>Prelacy;</hi> as it was objected firſt againſt the <hi>Presbyterians</hi> becauſe of the miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demeanour of Mr. <hi>Baxter,</hi> who pretends to the Monopoly of <hi>Presbytery,</hi> arrogating to himſelf the anteſignation and repreſentment of all the reſt.</p>
               <p>The Vanity of <hi>D. E.</hi> his firſt exception is ſufficiently diſcovered; I ſhall alſo make bare the inſufficiency of the reſt.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="exception">
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:55433:8"/>
               <head>II. EXCEPT.</head>
               <p>OUR Pamphleter takes it very ill that the Biſhop of <hi>Worceſter ſhould call himſelfe the ſole Paſtor of all the Congregations in his Dioceſe.</hi> Deeming that ſuch a poſition muſt needs be defended by the Arguments produced in behalfe of the <hi>Pope's</hi> Supremacy. I wonder, what could introduce into his thoughts ſuch a concluſion? or what could ſuggeſt that the ſame muſt be the Reaſon for a Biſhops ſuperintendency over one particular Dioceſe, and in ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordination to his <hi>Majeſty's</hi> command; and for the <hi>Pope</hi> to aſſume the univerſall command of all churches, without the acknowledgement of any higher Power to which he ſhould ſubmitt? I wonder whence <hi>D. E.</hi> derives ſuch dreams, as that there ſhould be a parity of reaſon and Convenience, for his <hi>Holyneſſe's</hi> governing the Church by ſuch a populous plurality of Subſtitutes, as that it is utterly impoſſible for him to make particular inquiſition into the execution of their functions; And for A <hi>Biſhop's</hi> adopting to himſelfe a limited number of deputies, whoſe more neighbouring deportments he may with much facility ſurvay and determine of them according to their known actions? What will any man judge but that <hi>D. E.</hi> his witts were at <hi>Rome</hi> all this while? But he informes us <hi>That he forbears to urge how contrary this Practice is to the Doctrine of the Apoſtles Paul, and Peter</hi> (<hi>hoping the</hi> Biſhop <hi>will not take it angrily, that he did not call them</hi> Saints, <hi>Since that theſe holy men did not need any ſtyle of honour out of the the Pope's Kalender</hi> The Saints are very little oblig'd to the Charity of this irreverent fellow, who will not give them what they deſerve, but what they need; And their Neceſsities, not their Merits, muſt preſcribe a proporti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to their titles. But why do not Biſhops follow the Doctrine of theſe Apoſtles? <hi>Paul,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>had ſent for the Elders of the Church of Epheſus bidding them feed the Church
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:55433:8"/>of God over which (not be himſelfe by his ſole authority as, Biſhop of the Dioceſe</hi> but) <hi>the Spirit had made them</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> i. e. <hi>Overſeers.</hi> And did the Spirit (I wonder) immediately without any inſtrumentall Cooperation of St. <hi>Paul,</hi> make them overſeers? Or doth the Biſhop now pretend to make Men overſeers without any reſpect had to the Influence of the Spirit? Wherein then lies the difference between the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop's practiſe and the Apoſtles Doctrine? O, but <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> and <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>with them ſignifie the ſame.</hi> Tis true, ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times they did ſignifie the ſame yet they were not all<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes of the Same Extent. Every one that was <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> and no more, might in ſome ſenſe be calld <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> but not <hi>è converſo,</hi> Every Biſhop or overſeer could not be calld a <hi>Presbyter,</hi> and no more. For my part I will not envy the term <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> to the moſt undeſerving prieſt, in it's genuine ſignification. But withall, I would have <hi>D. E.</hi> know, that a Community of name doth not alwayes in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volve an indiſtinction of dignity, or a parity of degree; Elſe would I enquire, why St. <hi>Paul</hi>) who was alſo <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>) did ſo imperiouſly ſummon the reſt? Or what plea St. <hi>Peter</hi> could produce for his Commanding the miniſters to feed the Flock (as <hi>D. E.</hi> himſelfe tells us): Which two occurrences are ſo far from patronizing our <hi>Replicant's</hi> Aſseverations, that they utterly defeat them; Manifeſtly holding forth a diſparity of eminence and command. I would deſire him therefore to be inform'd, that Cuſtom is guilty neither of Blaſphemy nor hereſy (the Degrees being ſtill the ſame with thoſe of the Apoſtles) in the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtriction of the title. A Scholar (I will not ſay <hi>D. E.</hi>) knowes that <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> formerly was a word equally appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priated to men and Spirits, employ'd in embaſsies; but now the eminence of the latter hath engroſſ'd the Name, eſpecially in it's tranſlations; as likewiſe the <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>-neſs of the Biſhops office hath attracted the uſe of the title <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </p>
               <p>In the next place, we are told (to detract from the Epiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>copal power) that <hi>Whoever feed the flock are under Chriſt</hi> (<hi>Whom the Apoſtle terms the Chief-Shepheard) the next and
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:55433:9"/>immediate paſtours of the flock,</hi> though his wits were gone a wool-gathering, and now I have found them among the flock. In the firſt of his <hi>Exceptions</hi> he is ſtrongly provok'd againſt Biſhops; as detracting from his <hi>Majeſty's Eccleſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſtick</hi> prerogative: And yet here, he thinks it no impeach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to the Kings ſupremacy, to give the moſt inconſider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able prieſt the upper hand of him inſpiritualls. Twas well he diſcovered no more of his name than <hi>D. E.</hi> elſe this ſentence might chance to have made his neck crack, ſince it ſavours little better than reaſon. For I would willingly know of him, whether the Paſtour of the Flock be not the Governour of the flock? If that he be (as he cannot de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny it), then, whoſoever feeds that flock is next and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately under Chriſt ſupream governour in Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cals, and the immediate head of the Church next to God; for <hi>D. E.</hi> tells us that he is the immediate, and, conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently, next to God, the ſupream Paſtour. So farewell to one of his Majeſty's titles. Is not this to be a moſt affectionate lover of the Kings perſon and Government, as he elſewhere pretended? But he tells us moreover, that, <hi>To extend the power beyond the actuall care of feeding, is a Notion altogether unſcripturall.</hi> Unleſs I am as farre out of the way as our Authour and Animadvertour is out of his wits, here is a falſe <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>; wherein he takes it for granted that a Biſhops care is not actuall. How unwarily doth he confound thoſe two termes <hi>actuall</hi> and <hi>Immediate</hi> (which laſt he would have ſaid, and ſo have excluded the Kings power from moſt parochiall congregations in Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land) thinking them of the ſame import and ſignifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. If <hi>D. E.</hi> did underſtand what, <hi>actuall,</hi> meant, he would know that a mediate care (ſuch as Epiſcop<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>l) is likewiſe actual. The word ſignifying nothing elſe than, exiſtent and in Act. Let us a little (for illuſtration) ſuppoſe an owner of a great flock dividing them into ſeverall parts, giving them to the tuition of one Paſtor; he diſtributing them to the Care of others, whoſe executing of their office he ſupreviſeth: Will <hi>D. E.</hi> ſay that this Supraviſour doth not take an actuall care of the flock? or that he is not the
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:55433:9"/>ſhepheard more immediate to the Owner? Or that he may not diſpoſe of the more inferiour paſtours <hi>pro arbitrio,</hi> alwayes reſpecting their actions and his Maſter's permiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion; Or that there is the ſame reaſon for ones feeding by vicegerents, whom by reaſon of their multitude and remotion he cannot overſee; and for another's depu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of feeders, whom by reaſon of their paucity and vicinity he may eaſily ſurvey? I think he will not, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though his indiſcretion and malevolence might counſell him to the aſsertion.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="exception">
               <head>III. EXCEPT.</head>
               <p>HE calls it <hi>A light and unſeemly trifling with ſacred Writ to underſtand the words ſpoken concerning th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſe that go not in by the door (and are therefore theeves and Robbers) of ſuch Miniſters as preach to Congregations without the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop's licenſe.</hi> Little dreams he, that they are called theeves and (Robbers not as preaching only to Congregations, for ſo they do but come in the wrong way, but) as they preach out of a deſigne to prejudice and plunder the true Shep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heard. And indeed ſuch poſtick irruptions imply ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of a malevolent Complexion; and the enſuing practiſes of ſuch intruders have bin an ample Comment on thoſe preceding deſignes that encourag'd them to the At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt. But he tels us that, <hi>If beſides ordination there muſt be a Licenſe, then</hi> (1) <hi>He knows not what Ordination mean's.</hi> Indeed I am eaſily induc'd to believe this latter Clauſe. He doth not know, that ther's a difference between the power and the place of Miniſtration, the Capacity and the place wherein to execute the Capacity. The Dignity and office of feeding is conferred at Ordination, but not the power to feed where he liſt, but where he ſhould have leave; leſt he ſhould treſpaſſe upon other mens incloſures, and undermine and ſupplant other pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtours, (2) Saith he, <hi>For one Miniſter of the Goſpell (for Certainly a Biſhop is no more).</hi> No certainly, he is no more then one, unleſs he had the <hi>Presbyterian</hi> faculty of a double
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:55433:10"/>heart and a double tongue: But yet this one is of a more dilated power and pre-eminence; but what of him? <hi>For him to ſilence his Fellow-Miniſter</hi> (But fellow-miniſter is not <hi>hayl fellow well met;</hi> they are fellows in the ſame function, but not in the ſame degrees of Dignity in that function), <hi>for no other reaſon but for preaching without a new licenſe</hi> (A new licenſe? pray firſt let them have an old one) <hi>this is an abuſe of dominion and contrary to the firſt ages of the Church.</hi> This we muſt take <hi>gratis, D. E.</hi> being as farre unacquainted with primitive tranſactions, as he is at defiance to ſound Reaſon. What if <hi>D. E.</hi> never read of ſuch a practiſe in the Church, doth it therefore neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily follow, that there was no ſuch practiſe? Or, what if there was no ſuch Cuſtome? Are there no cuſtomes laudable, but adequately thoſe which decayed Antiquity hath bequeathed us? Probably, the tender and Infant-Church could not away with a diſcipline ſo accurate, as that which it's more Virile-conſtitution doth exact. The uninquiſitive humours of men in thoſe dayes, contented themſelves in the fruition of the Goſpel, without any pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity to Schiſm. Men being more ſedulous in perſwading to a down-right faith, did not then require ſuch Cautions towards their preaching, as the now adays unſatisfy'd Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rioſities, which byaſs'd-men towards diſtraction, ſeem to call for.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Our Saviour</hi> (ſaith our Animadverter) ſilenc'd the Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſes by ſtrength of Argument, <hi>Which the Biſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>p of Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſter may do, when he is able.</hi> I confeſſe, he would have a difficult task, and <hi>D. E.</hi> may defye all Chriſtendome upon the Same account. For the beſt hopes in ſuch an enterpriſe would find unhappy fruſtration. For they may as well pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume to ſilence Thunder, as by rationall perſwaſions to ſtop the mouths of thoſe clamorous <hi>Presbyterians;</hi> who before they will, by a reaſonable Silence, ſeem to relinquiſh their long ſince defeated Cauſe, will not ſtick to croud whole Volumes with abſurdities; And rather then they'l appeare deſtitute of a Reply, their Adverſary ſhall hear of them in <hi>D E.</hi> his railing Dialect, and in <hi>Huckſters</hi> Rheto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rick.
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:55433:10"/>The only way then, of ſilencing ſuch, muſt be by conſtraint. O but, <hi>Our Saviour was ſo farr from Silencing the Phariſees from preaching, that he commands his diſciples both to hear and obey their Doctrine.</hi> But it was to obey their Doctrine, as (1) they preached the Law, not as they vented Schiſm and declared Faction. (2) Twas compara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tively, rather to ſquare their lives by the Phariſees doctrine than by their practſe, that Chriſt enjoyned his diſciples<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> (3) 'Twas to vouchſafe the Phariſees audience, as they were legally authorized, and becauſe they ſate in Moſes chaire: ſo that the Reaſon is of a farre different aſpect for the not forbidding of the Phariſees, and the toleration of <hi>Mr Baxter.</hi> Moreover (4) the Phariſees preach'd the <hi>Prophets,</hi> which Prophets diſcovered the <hi>Meſſiah;</hi> and ſo their preaching might advance <hi>Chriſt</hi>'s Kingdome: whereas the preaching of Nonconformiſts and ſuch like, would be ſo farr from promoting, that it would bury <hi>Chriſt</hi>'s King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome in the ruines of a diſtracted Church and a divided Realm. But briefly, ſince the ends of our Saviour's role<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rating the <hi>Phariſees</hi> are not fully known, conveniency ought ſomewhat more to be reſpected, than imitation in this matter. For, ſhould there be a ſufferance of preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, though (with the <hi>Phariſees</hi>) blaſpheming; why might not there be an indulging forbearance allowable to perſons o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> miniſters, though morally and notoriouſly offending? Which thing <hi>D. E.</hi> himſelf (pag. 5. lin. 2.) acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledgeth, as ſufficient ground of Silencing and ejection.</p>
               <p>I wiſh therefore that <hi>D. E.</hi> and the reſt of his tribe (if any be ſo ſimple and inconſiderate to be of his Society) would remember, that as, they ſpeake evill of Dignities, and reſiſt the Power which God hath ordained: ſo, they ſhall receive their due reward (though no ſatisfaction) for it? As likewiſe for all ſuch Pamphlets publiſh'd by them for the propagation of Sedition.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="exception">
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:55433:11"/>
               <head>IV. EXCEPT.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>HOw conſiſtent with the Civill Peace (for as to Chriſtian Charity he thinks the whole thing but a letter of defiance againſt it) the Biſhops diſtinction is about the Act of Indem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, He Hopes his Majeſty will in due time conſider. For the Biſhop,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>is ſo hardy as to tell us, that though the King had pardoned the Corporall puniſhment; yet the Church ought not to remit the Scandall till amends were made by Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion.</hi> 'Tis pitty but <hi>D. E</hi> were of his Majeſty's privy Councell, that he might prove his remembrancer. But I pray, what Reaſon is there, why he who hath bin prejudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall to the Church ſhould not make a due acknowledg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of his delinquency, before his re-admiſſion to his for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer priviledges? Is there not a grand diſcrimination between the remiſſion of a man's puniſhment, and the re-admiſſion into preferment? We ought to do good to out enemies in forgiving private injuries, but not in pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moting, them ſo long as by their non-recantation they ſeem to avow their former fact, and to maintain a poſture contradictory to the Churche's welfare. And how is this Diſtinction repugnant to the Civill Peace? Or rather, Is it not more adverſant thereunto, to preferre the men or forget the injury, when they not confeſſing do adhere to their for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer principles? This were for the Church, only to take care that thoſe (who are in a ſtrong probability of doing her an injury) ſhould be put in a Capacity to effect any of their deſignes; or at leaſt to contribute to their ſecurity by taking no notice of them. The Church exacting a Recantation reſpects not ſo much their paſt faults as their preſent poſture of Hoſtility. But Alas! what doth this word, Church, meane? Here <hi>D. E. could have wiſhed thas the Biſhop would have ſpoken out of the Clouds, and Plainly told whether By the Church, he meant a Congregation of the faithfull; or Archbiſhops, Biſhops</hi> &amp;c. I ſee I am miſtaken, for I thought that <hi>D. E.</hi> his foggy braine could have ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehended
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:55433:11"/>things ſpoken in a Cloud, better than thoſe deliver'd in the cleer Sunſhine. Well: If I might preſume to gueſse at the <hi>Reverend Father's</hi> meaning, I would tell <hi>D. E.</hi> that by the word, Church, he underſtands neither the Congregation, excluding Archbiſhops, Biſhops &amp;c. nor yet theſe, abſtracted from the Congregation, but both to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether. So that <hi>D. E.</hi> (though ignorantly) play's the Sophiſter, arguing <hi>à benè conjunctis ad malè diviſa.</hi> Hence 'tis that he labours with a falſe Suppoſition, That <hi>Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biſhops, Biſhops</hi> &amp;c. did exact a recantation, as perſons diſtinct from the Congregation; whereas they only act as Chiefs, Governours, and Repreſentatives of the reſidue of the Church or Congregation. Now if <hi>D. E.</hi> will ſay that the Congregation hath no Coercive power at all (as he doth aſſert), then would I fain know, By what power the antient Church excommunicated; whether it were not by conſtraint and force? which (if, <hi>D. E.</hi> underſtands the word) is all one with Coercive. Yea but,</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Why ſhould the Church force a Recantation for ſuch things as the King and Parliament commanded never more to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membred?</hi> Alas man, we look not ſo much on the Acts of hoſtility already preterlapſed and forgiven; as on thoſe whereunto they ſtand in a readineſſe, ſo long as they declare themſelves, unconvinc'd of their Crimes; I know that the non-conformiſts or others (who have manifeſted their activity in the late commotions) have their actions forgiven them; but the remiſſion of paſt facts, doth not ſecure the Church for futurity, ſo long as their non-recanting ſeem's to approve their precedent actings, and to warrant any other proceedings to come, of the ſame na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture. The Church may and doth forgive offences paſt, but is not bound to diſpenſe with thoſe preſent poſtures, that ſeem to allow the late extravagancies, and to maintain the Scandall. But we are ask'd, <hi>What can more enrage men to take wild and forbidden Courſes than so ſee preachers ſtrive to widen their wounds, and contrary to their former profeſſions pull off the plaiſters which the State, Phyſicians had provided for our diſtempers?</hi> Had our Pamphleter meant this of the
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:55433:12"/>
                  <hi>Presbyterian</hi> faction, the expreſſions had been appoſite, and well applyed to their Natures. But ſince his owne conſtruction, will ſcarce authorize or aſſent to ſo much truth, We ſhall anſwer his Quaery with another Interroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory. What then can more force a Conſtraint than to ſee ſuch preachers as Mr. <hi>Baxter,</hi> (contrary to their iterated declarations) vent ſedition, and not only widen the wounds of the Church, but even make them ſtink? I'me ſure, ſuch Empiricks as theſe, deſerve a purgation. As for <hi>D. E.</hi> I think him to be dangerouſly troubled with black Choler, for the remedy whereof he hath vomited prety largely againſt the Fathers of the Church; And as ſoon as the humour ſhall increaſe to the redintegration of his diſtem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, we muſt expect ſuch another Evacuation.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="exception">
               <head>V. EXCEPT.</head>
               <p>WIth what irreverence doth <hi>D. E.</hi> grumble, and call it bold and impious, to aſſert, <hi>That if to command an act, which by accident may prove the occaſion of ſin, be ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, then God himſelfe can command nothing?</hi> Since, ſaith he, <hi>A thing which by accident may be ſinfull, may be unlaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full in another to command for want of ſufficient Authority.</hi> And ſo is every thing elſe; Though we ſhould ſuppoſe an Injunction utterly devoyd of Sin, either in it ſelfe or in it's conſequences; yet would be unlawfull, if proceeding from an unlawfull Authority. So that we ſee that <hi>D. E.</hi> never ſpeaks but when his Mouth's open. He gives us a very good reaſon, why a thing may be unlawfull, viz, becauſe it may be unlawfull. The Queſtion is, Whether a thing may be unlawfull, as it may ocaſion ſin? <hi>D. E.</hi> anſwers, that it may be unlawfull as it proceeds from an unlawfull power. The Quaere is, Whether a thing that is ſinfull <hi>per accidens,</hi> under that formality and <hi>eò quòd</hi> ſinfull <hi>per accidens,</hi> be lawfull to be commanded? And he tells us, 'Tis un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawfull, <hi>eò quòd</hi> the Authority is unlawfull. We enquire, whether a command be illegitimate, becauſe the thing com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:55433:12"/>is ſinful accidentally and by conſequence? And he replies, that the command is illegitimate, becauſe the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority commanding is ſo. Which how much it is <hi>ad Rhom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bum,</hi> let any rational man conſider. And how little it impeaches the <hi>Lord Biſhops</hi> conſequence, the weakeſt capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>city may ſee. Still then it remains unſhaken, that if a thing being ſinful by conſequence be ground ſufficient to render a thing unlawfull; God himſelf can command nothing, ſince he cannot command any thing but what may by con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequence be made ſin.</p>
               <p>Beſides, <hi>D. E.</hi> goes againſt all rules of diſpute falling upon the <hi>hypotheſis of the Queſtion,</hi> for (the diſpute being concerning his Majeſty) they ſuppoſed the power comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to be lawfull and beyond exception. Only, our Pam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phleter had a mind tacitly to hint out treaſon to us, and to whiſper an illegitimacy entaild on the Kings Authority, and conſequently on all his edicts and <hi>Mandamus</hi>'s</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="exception">
               <head>VI. EXCEPT.</head>
               <p>I Cannot but think it a reaſonable and very ſolid Poſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Lord Biſhop, <hi>That an offence to which a diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proportionable penalty is annexed, is not to be meaſured by the abſtracted Quality of the Act, but by the miſchievous Conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quences it may produce.</hi> Since the forfeiture ought alwaies to bear proportion to the danger, and a greater penalty ſhould be proclaimed to ſcare men from ſuch actions, which (though puny and contemptible in themſelves) are attended with populous and peſtilent inconveniencies. But our wiſe Pamphleter is ſure, <hi>that in Divinity nothing is more falſe and dangerous. Hey, pas, preſto!</hi> Here ye ſhall have me, and there ye ſhall have me. In the firſt <hi>Exception, D. E.</hi> preſents himſelf in a grey coat, and the falſe beard of a Laick, But here he perſonates another man, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tends to Divinity. How doth he make himſelf an Ambo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dexter, an Hermaphrodite of Religion: A two fac'd
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:55433:13"/>pump, <hi>hinc Angelum ferens, illinc Cacodaemonem?</hi> He would ſerve for a good poſt in croſſe-waies, directing to ſeverall roads at once. I never took him for any other than a Fool in a Play, and he to juſtifie my conjecture hath here pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced his Coat of ſeveral colours; I will not ſay, it ſhews like <hi>Kiderminſter ſtuffe.</hi> But this I am ſure, <hi>D. E.</hi> is a <hi>Linſey-Woolſey</hi> Pamphleter. But pray let's hear the reaſon why his <hi>Lordſhip's</hi> aſſeveration is falſe in Divinity? <hi>viz. Becauſe to impoſe in the worſhip of God, as neceſſary circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances of it, things confeſſedly trivial and needleſſe is not ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtifiable.</hi> (1). I wonder to what old woman <hi>D. E.</hi> was lately Confeſſour? for I think none elſe would ever have made an acknowledgment that the things were trivial and needleſs, which ſhould be, or are, impoſed. Becauſe that we aſſert that things, though of ſmall moment in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, may have annexed to them dangerous conſequen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, therefore <hi>D. E.</hi> collects that we confeſſe them tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viall or needleſſe. But (2). Doth not our Author admira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly prove the falſity of the Lord Biſhop's poſition? Is not his conſequence ſtrong? To impoſe things trivial and need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe is not juſtifiable; Ergo an offence to which a diſpro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portionable penalty is annexed; muſt not be judged of by it's dangerous conſequences. <hi>D. E.</hi> ſpeaks nothing to the purpoſe, Ergo, His Lordſhips propoſition is falſe in Divinity, And actions ſhould not be judged of by their danger. Yea but</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The Church and it's peace, is much more endangered by the preſſing of ſuch things doubtfull.</hi> I wonder who told <hi>D. E.</hi> That the indifference of any of theſe things (<hi>viz.</hi> impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Circumſtances) were queſtionable or doubtful? or if they were doubtful, who told him that it was not in the Churches power, or that it was not her duty to determine of them? Or that it would incurre perill by impoſing them? I ſhould rather ſuppoſe, that the not giving men leave to diſſent in ſmall matters, would keep them from taking oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion to cauſe a diviſion in things of greater importance. Whereas the gratifying ſome with a little toleration, hath, and would again, animate either them or others to attempt
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:55433:13"/>Schiſms of greater bulke and proportion. The allowance of an inch makes many preſume on an ell. But I pray thee (candid Reader) lend me a little of thy ſpleen to laugh at a pretty expreſſion of our Pamphleter. <hi>From ſuch impoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>it follows, that (though we ought not) yet we lawfully may refuſe to ſubmit unto them.</hi> A man, it ſeems, ought not to rebell, but yet he lawfully may rebell. <hi>D. E.</hi> ought not to ſhew his back to the drumme head, and undergoe the Laſh, but yet <hi>D. E.</hi> lawfully may do it. But why may we lawfully refuſe to ſubmit to impoſitions of this nature, <hi>viz. Becauſe our Saviour did ſo, in not waſhing his hands before meat; And the Apoſtle</hi> (I think he means St. <hi>Paul) in the caſe of Circumciſion</hi> But I conceive, our Saviour refuſed to waſh, not in diſobedience to the Cuſtome, ſo much as to ſhew them the falſity of the reaſon whereon they built their Cuſtome, <hi>ſcil.</hi> Suppoſing that eating with unwaſhen hands defiled a man; Which opinion our Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Saviour refuted by telling the Jewes, that (not what went in, but) what came out from the man occaſioned his pollution. Beſides we do not read that waſhing of hands was ratify'd by Authority, but only introduced by frequent practiſe and tradition. So that Chriſt only ran counter to a cuſtome, and that will no way authorize our contradict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing an impoſition. As for that of St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s refuſing to cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſe, 'twas to ſhew the abolition of that Sacrament by the introduction of a new, and this is no preſident for non-conformiſts to refuſe ſubſcription to circumſtances of long continuance, and of neceſſary injunction, having not the authority of the Meſſiah for the introduction of any new ones in their room. Moreover we know that St. <hi>Paul</hi> did circumciſe <hi>Timothy,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Act. 16.1, 2, 3.</note> that he might not give occaſion of ſcandall to the Jewes, among whom he then was. If then <hi>D. E.</hi> will needs make the Apoſtle a pattern for i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitation in his non-conforming to an aboliſh'd Sacrament, and refuſing to circumciſe <hi>Titus</hi> when he was among the Gentiles. I ſee not but why I may with farre greater rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon urge his Example on the contrary. And ſince St. <hi>Paul</hi> being among the Jews did circumciſe, therefore we may
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:55433:14"/>well conclude, that amongſt Conformiſts we ought to conforme.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="exception">
               <head>VII EXCEPT.</head>
               <p>THe Sorites (which <hi>D. E.</hi> termes a Chayn of conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quences) uſed by the Lord Biſhop to prove the neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity of impoſition, are (to ſpeake Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi>'s Language) the words of truth and Soberneſſe. viz. <hi>From diverſity in externall rights reſulteth diſlike, thence enmity, thence oppoſition, thence Schiſm in Church, and ſedition in State. The State not ſtanding ſecure without the Church, nor the Church without unity, nor unity without uniformity, nor uniformity without ſtrict impoſition.</hi> To this <hi>D. E.</hi> anſwers, <hi>That it is a meer rope of Sand</hi> (A pretty good Anſwer for one that was gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vell'd. Somewhat 'twas that <hi>D. E.</hi> was angry with it, he ſtanding not well affected to any Rope but one of Hemp). But he proceds: <hi>And the parts of his chaine</hi> (it ſeems, a Rope and a Chaine are all one with our Animal: Indeed they are ſomething of Kin, and, if he proceed in his begun courſes, the Chaine may chance to bring him to the Rope). Well but what of the parts? why they <hi>do as little hang together, as Samſon's Foxes did before they were tyed by the Tayles</hi> (I thought ſomething of a Foxe was nigh, the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe did ſo ſtink) <hi>which courſe the Biſhop hath imituted, not forgetting to put in even the firebrand it ſelfe to make up the Compariſon.</hi> So that this Fellow will needs make the Biſhops book the firebrand. Well, be it ſo, The fire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brand came betwixt the two tayles; The Lord Biſhop's book came between the Book of Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> and <hi>D. E.</hi> his Pamphlet; how eaſily then hath <hi>D. E.</hi> prov'd that thoſe two laſt were the fox-tayles. And indeed the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pariſon is cloſe and genuine, ſince either of them have left a moſt abominable ſcent behind them. But to prove the inſufficiency of his <hi>Lordſhip's Sorites,</hi> we are preſented with three obſervations.</p>
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:55433:14"/>
               <p n="1">(1.) That <hi>there ought to be diverſity in external formes, ſince the Apoſtles of the Circumciſion gave the right hand of followſhip to the Apoſtle of the Gentiles.</hi> What then? Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the Apoſtles of the <hi>Jews,</hi> and thoſe of the <hi>Gentiles</hi> did agree; <hi>ergo,</hi> there ought to be diverſity of external forms. Still the old coneſquences! Yea, but they did agree, <hi>Although the external forms of worſhip were far more different than thoſe of England.</hi> (1.) I'le enquire of <hi>D. E.</hi> where he heard, how he proves, or when he dream'd it? (2.) I'le ask him, what of all that, though we ſhould ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe a difformity in their worſhip? Peradventure the State of an infant-Church requir'd it. And (though, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bably, they did not approve of diverſity in Circumſtanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>als, yet) they would not wrangle about Formalities, leſt they ſhould deterr others from the Fundamentals. But now the caſe is alter'd, and a diſpenſation for recuſancy in Circumſtance, is ſo far from gayning others to the Funda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentals, that it encourageth thoſe who have already re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived the Faith, to the mangling of the Church, and the disjoyning of Chriſt's Myſtical Body.</p>
               <p n="2">(2.) He tells us, <hi>That the State may be preſerv'd with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the Church, as it is evident in thoſe</hi> 300 <hi>years before</hi> Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantine, <hi>when there was no Church at all legally Counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nanced.</hi> Still we are troubled with a groſſe <hi>Non-ſequitur.</hi> As if there were the ſame reaſon for a Church newly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oculated and a Church concorporated with the State; when the Church, as ſuch, bears an equall weight with the State, as ſuch. Before <hi>Conſtantine,</hi> though all the Church had been maſſacred, yet might the temporall State have ſtood, yea and triumphed in their bloud; Since thoſe that had the Management of Secular affaires were not members of the Church. But now when diſcrepancy of worſhip proves matters of faction; when all that rule in, or ſubmit to, the temporall State, muſt (as alſo Church-members) parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipate and ſhare in the fortunes of one or other part of the Church; the downfall of the one unavoydably involves the diſſolution of the other. So that when the frabrick of the Church, decayes in a Voluminous ruine, the State muſt
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:55433:15"/>alſo crack in a proportionable Emphaſis of a broken frame.</p>
               <p n="3">3. <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity in heart and ſpirit doth not in the leaſt depend upon <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niformity but on charity,</hi> i. e. <hi>A Chriſtian and candid forbearance in things circumſtantiall, while we agree in eſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tialls.</hi> I admire, in what Authour <hi>D. E.</hi> read this defi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nition of Charity? we uſe to terme it, <hi>Amare Deum, ſupra omnia, propter ſeipſum; &amp; vicinum, aequè ac noſmet, propter Deum.</hi> So that the part of charity looking towards our Neighbour, teacheth us to love him as our ſelves, but ſtill for God's ſake. Now, whether this Charity depends upon unity, and conſequently on uniformity, or elſe Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and uniformity on Charity, will eaſily appear. If the breach of charity hangs upon diſunion, and diſunion up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on difformity; then Charity dedends upon union, and union on uniformity: But the Antecedent is manifeſtly true, that the rending of the Church breaks the bonds of Charity, in that it detracts from the honour of God; with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out which, the love of our Neighbour is no Charity: and that this rending or diſunion depends on difformity, in that difference of circumſtantials cauſeth heart-burnings, and an moſities. Whereupon <hi>D. E.</hi> is clearly miſtaken in the dependance; Charity depending on, and being propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion'd to Unity, not Unity to Charity. But what if we ſhould concede Unity to depend on Charity? yet ſtill <hi>D. E.</hi> is in his old <hi>non ſequitur.</hi> For Unity would ſtill de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pend (though mediately) on Uniformity, ſince Charity (whereon he would have Unity depend) would be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved by Uniformity, and broken by Difformity. <hi>D. E.</hi> his candid forbearance then of one another in Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantials, is ſo far from being Charity, that it is the infringe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of it; ſince ſuch a forbearance or connivence at Non-conformiſts, would, by the rending of the Church (which would unavoydably follow) tend to Gods diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>honour. But <hi>D. E.</hi> is not farther out in this, than in that which follows: viz. <hi>The Warrs did not ariſe from the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paration of Conſcientious diſſenters</hi> (in this he ſpeaks truth, for it was not Conſcience, but Obſtinacy counſelled them
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:55433:15"/>to diſſent) <hi>but from the fury of unconſcionable impoſers.</hi> But ſure it was diſſenting cauſed the rigid impoſing. And then if it muſt be Impoſing that broach'd the Warres, it may thanke forward Diſſenting. Which ſame diſſenting practiſes whether they may not produce a relapſe into their former conſequences, I would fain have thoſe recuſants conſider; Unleſſe they delight in Animoſities, and like <hi>Salamanders</hi> long bath'd in flames diſguſt the influence of a milder Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="exception">
               <head>VIII. EXCEPT.</head>
               <p>D. <hi>E.</hi> Pretends to have great inſight into the Eccleſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſtick laws of the <hi>French</hi> and <hi>Dutch</hi> Proteſtants; (And probably he may, for his underſtanding hath been beyond ſea, a long time). But yet he never read of any <hi>Impoſition of ſtanding, ſitting, or any other poſture, at the Adminiſtration of the Euchariſt.</hi> But yet if there were, ſaith he, <hi>it doth not ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtifie our impoſition of kneeling.</hi> (1) <hi>Becauſe the queſtion is,</hi> de jure, <hi>whether it be lawfull for them to preſcribe any one po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſture. D. E.</hi> might do well to ſtep over, and convince thoſe Churches of their Errour. But why may not they enjoin one particular Poſture; ſince an <hi>Oleo</hi> and mixture of car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage at the reception of the Sacrament is not only unde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent; But (when every man ſhall adopt to himſelf a frame of deportment) they will approach the Lords Table ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with affectation, partially applauding their own judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, or elſe with regret maligne the diſſimilary compo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of others. Either of which are enough to render a Man an unworthy receiver. Beſides though ſome have made it their endeavour to prove the carriage of the Apoſtles diſcrepant from ours; Yet none ever dream'd that they had a plurality of poſtures among themſelves. (2). Saith <hi>D. E. None of thoſe poſtures,</hi> uſ'd by other Churches, <hi>are ſo lyable to exception, as kneeling.</hi> I anſwer, that they are more lyable to exception, Sitting partaking much of ir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reverence;
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:55433:16"/>and ſtanding being not ſuch an ample expreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of humility and devotion. In <hi>kneeling</hi> there is an obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation of Decency. For conſidering the importance of the ordinance, and the Majeſty of the perſon with whom we have to do; I know no reaſon but that the moſt ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſe and reverential ſituation of the body ſhould (even proſcinded from an enjoyning power) be obligatory, and more than indifferent.</p>
               <p>But why is kneeling ſo liable to Exception? (1) <hi>Becauſe it varies moſt from the old form.</hi> Believe him who will! Which, I pray, doth <hi>ſtanding, ſitting,</hi> or kneeling more bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der on diſcumbency? But what though it ſhould moſt dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer from the old form? although <hi>D. E.</hi> cannot prove it. They in their demeanours conſulted conveniency; we, to expreſſe our devotion. But (2) <hi>Kneeling hath been mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrouſly abuſ'd by the Papiſts to Idolatry.</hi> What though? doth the abuſe of a thing argue the illegitimacy of it's uſe? I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve then that <hi>D. E.</hi> never ſaith his Praiers on his knees. Or probably he ſaith them in his ſleep, becauſe waking praiers were abuſ'd by Papiſts in their Vigils; and it may be, this made many Presbyterians wink and pray. Or (which is moſt likely) <hi>D. E.</hi> never ſaith any Praiers at all, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe Papiſts have made the Saints groan with their innu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merable Supplications, and have made Pictures the Objects of clamorous Peritions. <hi>D. E.</hi> ſure never puts the Bible to the penance of a conſultation, becauſe the moſt dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned Hereticks have father'd their pretenſions thereon, and have had recourſe to Scripture for the Patronage of their Poſitions.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="exception">
               <head>IX. EXCEPT.</head>
               <p>D. <hi>E.</hi> complains again of the injury was done in revi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling the whole body of <hi>Presbyterians for the faults of Mr.</hi> Baxter, <hi>upon ſuppoſition that he is a Presbyterian.</hi> Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition that he is a Presbyterian? Why will any think o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe?
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:55433:16"/>I cannot conceive but Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> would repute it a Calumny of the greateſt Magnitude, for any to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude him out of the number, nay not to ſuppoſe him their ringleader. Do not others, (yea and his own over-weening fancy) look on him as the pillar of their reeling Cauſe? Do not all ſtand indicted of He eſie in the thoughts of the reſt, who ſwarve from his poſitions, and comply not with an eager ſubſcription to what he depoſeth? It ſeems (though <hi>D. E.</hi> ſcruples not to affirm it) the Age is not too wiſe to be gull'd with an <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. But our Animadverter would have every man <hi>bear his own burden.</hi> And (although he doth not expreſſe it, yet) he hath a pretty good reaſon for ſuch a requeſt, for he knows Presbyterians to be of that ſort of Animals which is very good at bearing. But he wonders, in <hi>what Bible the Biſhop found that he might aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſe a whole order of men for the pretended miſcarriage of one?</hi> I wonder in what book (I will not ſay Bible, for I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jecture that he little troubles that) did <hi>D.</hi> E. read that a man might not reprove a whole Society, for the reall miſdemeanour of their ſuppoſed Chieftain? Or, where did he find that there is reaſon to rebandy the phraſe— <hi>Crimine ab uno Diſce omnes,</hi> upon the order of Epiſcopacy, becauſe of the Lord of <hi>Worceſter's</hi> dreamed fault; ſince he pretends not to ſuch an univerſality on the one ſide, as Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> doth on the other. But not to gratifie the pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tulant and Sawcy humour of our Pamphleter, I would be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech him to know that the Sentence by him retorted, is ſo farre from extending to <hi>Diſce omnes,</hi> that it is not yet come to <hi>Crimine ab uno.</hi> And <hi>D. E.</hi> is ſo farre from truly introducing the reſt of the Biſhops as guilty, that he hath not yet prov'd one of them Criminal.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Hitherto D. E.</hi> tells us, <hi>he was willing to propoſe his ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptions</hi> (or rather to blazon his ignorance) <hi>but he will leave it to ſome abler pen</hi> (as he had need) <hi>to convince the Biſhop and the world that it is not now time to ſow tares.</hi> No nor any other ſeed, ſo long as there are ſuch Geeſe as <hi>D. E.</hi> to devour it. I wonder what Seed this is which our Pamphle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:55433:17"/>hath ſowed? 'Tis ſcarce, ſo good as <hi>Infoelix lolium.</hi> It is ſome kin to hemp-ſeed, and may in time do him a courteſie in the return. But the Reaſon, I pray, why a man may not in this Age ſow tares? <hi>O, The Age is too wiſe to take every thing for Oracle which the Biſhop's paſſion dictates.</hi> No, nor yet whatever <hi>D.</hi> E. ſhall proclaim; although there be ſome Reaſon for it, Since the Spirit in him, ſpake (like that of <hi>Jupiter Hammon</hi>) out of an Image.</p>
               <p>But yet before parting, <hi>D. E.</hi> will give us a taſte <hi>of the Reverend Father's deep wiſdome.</hi> And I will ſee how well his ſhallow wit will be able to fathom it.</p>
               <p n="1">1. SAith <hi>D. E. The Biſhop declaimes ſo fiercely, as if he would crack his Girdle. Girdle?</hi> He was reſolv'd a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt ſo much non-ſenſe to have one word that was <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nonical.</hi> But in the ſpace doth he not ſtrain ſo hard his rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling vein, that he hath burſt that point whereto the waſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band of his Britches ſhould truſt, which makes him ſo fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cily liable to the Laſh? But what is that againſt which there are ſuch Declamations? <hi>viz. Againſt thoſe who force all Communicants to come unto them, and be particularly exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined before their Admiſſion to the Sacrament.</hi> And what can <hi>D. E.</hi> ſay againſt any mans exploding ſuch a Cuſtome? or in vindication of ſuch a Practiſe? Only this, <hi>That they were but examined once for all, as likewiſe the Biſhop allows Catechiſing.</hi> But I hope there is not the ſame reaſon for Catechizing, and for Presbyterian Examination; Catechi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zing being a facile and preſcribed way of informing men in their duty, and exhibiting to them a compendious means of knowing the opinion of the Church in matters of faith and practiſe. Whereas (1). Examinations, whereby <hi>Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byterians</hi> ſifted men, was many times in Queſtions unheard-of and peradventure ſcarce well underſtood of the exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner. As, <hi>How long have you been converted? What method did the Spirit uſe in your Converſion?</hi> And a multitude of Queries of the ſame Hackle. (2). The main thing that makes their Examination obvious to exception, is; In that
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:55433:17"/>the Miniſter had recourſe to his own private principles and ſingle perſwaſion for the Queſtions he propoſed; Inſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much that if the Anſwer were found to diſcover a glimpſe of an opinion that ſwarv'd from the Maxims of his private and pick'd Church, it did adminiſter ſufficient Occaſion of renunciation. Which practiſe how laudable it was, let any (but <hi>D. E.</hi>) judge. This <hi>D. E.</hi> thinks himſelf ingeni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous when he tells us next, <hi>That the Biſhop did well this cold weather to ſet up a man of ſtraw, and catch himſelf a heat with threſhing it.</hi> To ſee how much the Man's miſtaken! Tis I have been at the pains all this while to threſh this man of ſtraw, although I have not ſweat for't.</p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>D. E.</hi> thinks it inadvertency in the Lord Biſhops wiſh, <hi>That the Authors of all ſuch books as defend the Covenant would burn them themſelves to ſave the Hangman a labour.</hi> But I cannot enough applaud the Counſell. For the Sacrificing and devoting ſuch Books voluntarily to the flames, might in ſome degree expiate the Authours crimes in a burnt of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering. But as yet I ſee no reaſon any man hath (though our Pamphleteer thinks the contrary) to bawk the repeti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Covenant to the infamy of ſuch as perpetuate its remembrance, and keep the memory thereof enſhrin'd in thoſe unhappy ſheets, wherein they have wrapped it's Apology. I would not have <hi>D. E.</hi> dread the Dilemma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tical inconveniences that would accrue to thoſe who ſhould attempt the defence of that Oath. Let him not fear be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>goared with the hornes</hi> (as he phraſes it) of a <hi>Syllogiſmus cornutus,</hi> ſince an <hi>Argumentum baculium</hi> doth better ſuit with his capacity. But he hath a great tenderneſſe <hi>for the lawfull part of an Oath, after that it is ſolemnly taken.</hi> Here he hints to us that ſome part of the Covenant was lawful, and gives a ſilent approbation of ſomething in that, which the wiſdome of the Parliament wholly diſallowed. <hi>But it hath been taken by thoſe who have ventured their lives to ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nalize their Loyalty.</hi> But have not many of them ſince gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven a pregnant teſtimony how ill they have reſented the thing it ſelf, as alſo how utterly they deteſted that com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulſive power which forced it upon them, by a ſpontane<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:55433:18"/>and unengaged care for its abolition? Wherefore, (though <hi>D. E.</hi> like a friend, takes care for it's peaceable interment <hi>thinking it's Aſhes might have reſted quietly better than have blown about by the Biſhops furious breath, ſince it was burnt by publique Authority,</hi> yet) I would enquire, (Since <hi>THAT</hi> which was the Cinders from whence great flames had their eruption, and diſplay'd themſelves in a generall conflagration, is now reduc'd to aſhes) why ſhould thoſe Volumes that have engaged in it's patronage preſerve it's reliques unextinct, and gratifie the Covenant in a poſthume-life?</p>
               <p n="3">3. <hi>D. E. Can never enough commend the Biſhop's wiſdome in reſolving never to write again.</hi> And I can never ſufficiently applaud our Pamphleteer, who took courage to defie one, which not only ſcorn'd to foul his fingers with him, but alſo had determin'd not to anſwer. But that which <hi>D. E.</hi> Ironically ſpeaks; I ſeriouſly repeat, as ſeeing high <hi>wiſdome in his Lordſhip's reſolve againſt writing:</hi> For why ſhould he grate his daies, and waſte his Spirits in replying to the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>defatigable Lungs and pens of any railing Presbyterians. Since he might acquieſce in that plenary refuration of his detractour, and the ful ſatisfaction which his Letter contains and preſents to any that ſhould enquire into his belyed pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings with Mr. <hi>Baxter.</hi> And I think there's none can finde therein either errour or inſufficiency (as to the matter it comprehends) unleſſe ſuch as are of <hi>D. E.</hi> his inſolent and pedantique humour, which prompted him ſo magiſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rially to vent his Non-ſenſe, even to the glowing of a ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber eare. Such, I confeſſe (if there be any ſuch) as he may cry out (though ridiculouſly enough) <hi>that the Biſhops reſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved Silence reſembles a School boy, who after a box on the ear lent to another, cunningly retreats.</hi> But I ſhould ſuppoſe it ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther School-boy-like to give him a box on the eare whom he knows to be peremptorily reſolv'd againſt retaliation, and determin'd not to ſtrike again. How much doth this Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>militude of the Pamphleteer ſpeak the Author, and ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently evince his underſtanding to be <hi>ſub ferula?</hi> How doth his extravagant and <hi>nil ad rem</hi> treatiſe, argue that his witts
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:55433:18"/>play Truant? And his very name (<hi>viz. D. E.</hi>) import that he is in his <hi>A. B. C.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But to ſee the vaulting and ſalacious humour of our A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimadverter in the skipping of his compariſon: from a School-boy to a Gyant. If ſaith he, <hi>Goliah</hi> (he means the Biſhop) <hi>ſhall defy Iſrael, and retire from the field, with only ſhewing his teeth. The Philiſtins will hardly thank him.</hi> But I ſay, that if <hi>Goliah</hi> (I mean Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi>) armed with a weaver's beam (though in his eye) ſhall thunder defy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance againſt the <hi>King and his Hoſt,</hi> Why may not <hi>David</hi> retire upon the conqueſt of his <hi>Monſtrous foe?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But ſince <hi>D. E.</hi> pronounceth it not the part of a Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pion to ſhew his teeth only and and run away; I would ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſe him (when ever he is to engage with his Adverſary) not to ſhew his teeth, but his eares, the more formidable and ſcaring objects by farre. Our Author haſtening now towards an end, will <hi>not ſtand to determine whether the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portment of the Biſhop may make the reſt of the Prelates, judge him of kin to</hi> quickly-defeated <hi>Goliah or not?</hi> Neither will I conteſt much about it. Only <hi>D. E.</hi> his impudence per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwades me to believe himſelf of ſome affinity with <hi>Goliah. For Goliah</hi> had an helmet of braſſe, and our Champion's face is of the ſame mettal.</p>
               <p>Hitherto I have followed the Chaſe; But ſince the Dra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gooner hath pleaſ'd to retire to the protection of his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended honourable Patron, I ſhall leave both him and his Letter of intelligence to their Covert, expecting to hear farther the next return. Till when I ſhall preſume to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treat to the Garriſon of the Readers courteſie (from whence I firſt iſſued and) where I dare not deſpair of Security and Shelter.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
